Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Moving Images Collection FILMS.001
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series I. Transport Workers Union of America Films, 1930-1977; 34.5 Linear Feet in 16 record cartons and 177 film cans; 13.3 Gigabytes in 18 digital files
  - Subseries I.A. Films, 1930-1977
    - Automated Subway Train, circa 1960 (Film canister c113, 16mm film reels 001_0282)
      An inspection tour taken by TWU officers to look at the operation of a new kind of subway train.
    - District 65-RWDSU Strike Meeting, 1960 (Film canister c97, 16mm film reels 001_0229)
      At a meeting at their union (District 65-RWDSU) headquarters, employees of Stern's Department Store decide whether to call a strike.
    - Press Conference, 1960 (Box 19, Film canister c108, 16mm film reels 001_0412)
      Transport Workers Union's Michael Quill announces a strike against the Pennsylvania Railroad; Theodore Kheel interview.
    - Labor Day Parades, New York City, 1960-1961 (Box 22, 16mm film reels 001_0823)
      See the video reproduction cuid36997 in Subseries I.B.
      Shots from the 1960 and 1961 New York City Labor Day parades.
    - Mass Meeting, 1960-1961 (Box 32, 16mm film reels 001_0287, 001_0288)
      Michael Quill addresses Transport Workers Union meeting on attempted corporate takeover of Fifth Avenue Coach Company.
    - Railroad Strike, Labor Day Parade, 1960-1961 (Film canister c133, 16mm film reels 001_0265)
      Pickets and strike headquarters; Labor Day parade in New York City.
    - Philadelphia Railroad Strike and Brooklyn Union Gas Strike Footage, circa 1960-1964 (Film canister c166, 16mm film reels 001_0204)
      Series of clips related to TWU strikes against Pennsylvania Railroad and Brooklyn Union Gas Company. Includes: Douglas MacMahon speaks to strikers; New York City Mayor Robert Wagner interviewed by film producer Tom Costigan; Matthew Guinan speaking at press conference; Brooklyn Union Gas strike rally.
    - Philadelphia Transit Strike Clips, 1960-1967 (Film canister c235, 16mm film reels 001_0027)
      Philadelphia transit strike clips; bus driver driving bus; trains linking; bus or subway destination sign.
    - American Airlines Travel Films, circa 1960s (Film canister c153, 16mm film reels 001_0216)
      Two travel films produced for American Airlines in the early 1960's, one focusing on Los Angeles (00:00 - 4:30), the other on Chicago (9:13 - 13:40).
    - Pan American Airways Repair Shops, 1960s (Film canister c77, 16mm film reels 001_0314)
      Roughly follows sequence of airplanes being repaired/serviced in the shop, to being cleaned/checked before take-off, baggage put on board, take-off and landing.
    - Local 234 Negotiations with the Philadelphia Transportation Company, circa January, 1961 (Film canister c85, 16mm film reels 001_0226)
    - Local 234 Strike Victory Program, January 1961 (Film canister c48, 16mm film reels 001_0810)
      See the video reproduction cuid36998 in Subseries I.B.
    - Friday Meeting, April 14, 1961 (Film canister c77, 16mm film reels 001_0315)
      A negotiating session between union officials and management
    - Joint Executive Committee Meeting, circa May 1961 (Film canister c183, 16mm film reels 001_0217)
      Meeting of Transport Workers Union enlarged joint executive committee. Matthew Guinan addresses meeting; Ellis Van Riper reads a list of demands; Daniel Gilmartin speaks on automation; Douglas MacMahon speaks; Michael Quill speaks.
    - Local 234 Strike Victory in Philadelphia, June 1961 (Box 21, 16mm film reels 001_0852)
      Matthew Guinan and Ellis Van Riper speak at enlarged Transport Workers Union joint executive committee meeting.
    - Local 100 Meeting, June, 1961 (Box 25, 16mm film reels 001_0829)
      See the video reproduction cuid36999 in Subseries I.B.
      Trims of members speaking from floor at Transport Workers Union meeting; Transport Workers Union officers addressing same meeting off camera.
    - Mass Meeting, June 13, 1961 (Film canister c59, 16mm film reels 001_0804, Box 28, 16mm film reels 001_0825)
      See the video reproduction cuid37003 in Subseries I.B.
      Transport Workers Union leaders address mass meeting on subject of attempted corporate takeover of Fifth Avenue Coach Company.
    - Local 100 Mass Meeting, June 13, 1961 (Film canister c59, 16mm film reels 001_0805)
    - Demonstration Against Railroad Merger, June 26, 1961 (Box 17, Film canister c35, 16mm film reels 001_0382)
      TWU demonstration and automobile cavalcade against the Pennsylvania Railroad.
    - City Election Endorsements, August, 1961 (Box 22, 16mm film reels 001_0862)
      See the video reproduction cuid37000 in Subseries I.B.
      Democratic candidates for New York City mayor, comptroller, and president of the City Council address a meeting of the Transport Workers Union, to solicit its active support for their campaign.
    - TWU at Parade, August, 1961 (Film canister c1, 16mm film reels 001_0801)
      Transport Workers Union members leafletting on street at parade.
    - Robert Wagner Campaign Speech Outtakes, August 23, 1961 (Film canister c209, 16mm film reels 001_0172)
      Outtakes of campaign speeches by New York City mayor Robert Wagner and his running mates Paul Screvane and Abe Beame.
    - Robert Wagner Speaks at TWU Meeting, August 23, 1961 (Box 20, 16mm film reels 001_0859)
    - Mayor Wagner Endorsement, August 23, 1961 (Box 21, 16mm film reels 001_0858)
      At a meeting of the Transport Workers Union discussion includes desirability of political organizing and formation of a labor party, and Robert F. Wagner, Jr. is endorsed as candidate for mayor of New York City.
    - Labor Day Parade, September, 1961 (Box 34, 16mm film reels 001_0310, Film canister c87, 16mm film reels 001_0312)
    - Jimmy Hoffa speaks at 11th Biennial TWU Convention, October 2-6, 1961 (Box 18, Film canister c108, 16mm film reels 001_0409, Film canister c52, 16mm film reels 001_0860)
    - Mass Meeting, November, 1961 (Box 26, 16mm film reels 001_0836, 001_0837, 001_0838, 001_0839)
      See the video reproduction cuid37001 in Subseries I.B.
    - Michael Quill Press Release, November 21, 1961 (Box 28, 16mm film reels 001_0827)
      A filmed press release with three main takes, in which Michael Quill is interviewed about a threatened strike.
    - Mass Meeting with Michael Quill, December 28, 1961 (Film canister c214, 16mm film reels 001_0162)
      See the video reproduction cuid37002 in Subseries I.B.
    - Mass Meeting with Matthew Guinan, December 28, 1961 (Box 24, 16mm film reels 001_0841)
    - Brooklyn Union Gas Company Strike, 1961
      Strike rallies during Transport Workers Union strike against Brooklyn Union Gas Company.
      - Film (Box 24, 16mm film reels 001_0834)
      - Film (Box 24, 16mm film reels 001_0844)
      - Film (Film canister c58, 16mm film reels 001_0796)
        Transport Workers Union officers entering Gracie Mansion, theNew York City mayor's official residence; Transport Workers Union strikers picket Brooklyn Union Gas Company.
      - Film (Box 24, 16mm film reels 001_0833)
        Transport Workers Union leaders, including Douglas MacMahon, speak at a rally for striking Brooklyn Union Gas workers. Rally takes place in front of company headquarters.
    - Brooklyn Union Gas Company Press Conference, 1961 (Film canister c58, 16mm film reels 001_0795)
      Press conference at City Hall on Transport Workers Union strike against the Brooklyn Union Gas Company.
    - Gas Workers, circa 1961 (Film canister c109, 16mm film reels 001_0323)
      Includes interior shots of control rooms with closeups of dials, switches, screens, equipment and shots of workers.
    - Graphics and Animations, circa 1961 (Film canister c116, 16mm film reels 001_0339)
      Trims or outtakes of graphics and still cartoons representing contract demands or provisions of Transport Workers Union (including "No robot motormen, conductors, or mechanical railroad clerks").
    - Labor Day Parade, New York City, 1961 (Film canister c209, 16mm film reels 001_0173)
      Scenes from 1961 New York City Labor Day parade.
    - Labor Day Parade, New York City, 1961 (Film canister c52, 16mm film reels 001_0861)
      1961 Labor Day Parade--including footage of marchers down Fifth Avenue and facades of businesses, Transport Workers Union floats, parade spectators, and fife and drum corps.
    - Local 101 Rally Against Brooklyn Union Gas Company, circa 1961 (Box 24, 16mm film reels 001_0835)
      Rally for Transport Workers Union Local 101 against Brooklyn Union Gas Company.
    - Local 234 Strike Against Philadelphia Transportation Company, 1961 (Film canister c84, 16mm film reels 001_0228)
      All sequences relate to Transport Workers Union Local 234 strike against Philadelphia Transportation Company (PTC), except for sequence 7, which has to do with the union's strike against the Pennsylvania Railroad.
    - Mass Meeting, 1961 (Box 24, 16mm film reels 001_0842)
      Shots of audience.
    - Mass Meeting, Picket Signs, 1961 (Box 26, 16mm film reels 001_0843)
      Picket signs at meeting of Transport Workers Union.
    - Mass Meeting on Takeover of 5th Avenue Coach, 1961 (Box 34, 16mm film reels 001_0918)
      See the video reproduction cuid37004 in Subseries I.B.
      Transport Workers Union leadership presents proposal on how to combat a corporate takeover of the Fifth Avenue Coach Company to a mass meeting of the membership. Speakers include M. Guinan, D. Gilmartin, J. Donoghue
    - Opening Negotiations with NYCTA, circa 1961 (Box 20, 16mm film reels 001_0857)
      Michael Quill and other Transport Workers Union officers negotiating with the New York City Transit Authority
    - Opening Negotiations with NYCTA, circa 1961 (Box 16, Film canister c121, 16mm film reels 001_0396, 001_0397)
      Transport Workers Union press conference discussing presentation of wage demands to New York City Transit Authority.
    - Philadelphia Transit Company Strike, 1961 (Film canister c209, 16mm film reels 001_0174)
      Material relating to Transport Workers Union Local 234 strike against Philadelphia Transit Company (PTC).
    - Philadelphia Transit Company Strike, circa 1961 (Film canister c47, 16mm film reels 001_0822)
      Materials relating to Transport Workers Union strike against the Philadelphia Transit Company. Features Teamsters Union official Jimmy Hoffa addressing the strikers and participating in a press conference with TWU leader Michael Quill.
    - Philadelphia Transit Company Strike Clips, circa 1961 (Film canister c161, 16mm film reels 001_0183)
      Footage relating to Transport Workers Union strike against Philadelphia Transit Company.
    - Powerhouse Footage (Edited for TV), 1961 (Box 19, Film canister c108, 16mm film reels 001_0410)
      Edited footage of a control room, including industrial equipment, chutes, turbines, dials, screens, and people at work.
    - Press Conference, 1961 (Box 20, 16mm film reels 001_0854)
      Press conference by Transport Workers Union's Michael Quill on union's demands to New York City Board of Transportation or New York City Transit Authority.
    - Reports on Negotiations with Brooklyn Union Gas, 1961 (Film canister c58, 16mm film reels 001_0794)
      Transport Workers Union official reports on progress of negotiations with Brooklyn Union Gas officials.
    - Scenes related to Philadelphia transit strike, 1961 (Film canister c182, 16mm film reels 001_0202)
    - Trims, circa 1961 (Film canister c214, 16mm film reels 001_0163)
      Miscellaneous trims from Transport Workers Union footage, including a press conference with Douglas MacMahon speaking.
    - Years of Challenge, 1961
      A documentary film reporting on the Transport Workers Union's progress since its last convention, and the union's plans for the years ahead.
      - Complete film (Box 33, 16mm film reels 001_0909)
        This version is silent, but with superior visual quality.
      - Complete film (Box 21, 16mm film reels 001_0849)
      - Excerpts (Film canister c129, 16mm film reels 001_0249)
        Includes the shorts "Highest Wages for Transit Workers," "12 Paid Holidays," "The Bigger the Vote for TWU, the Better the Contract." Brief shots of trains, subway turnstiles, and change-making machines.
      - Outtakes (Box 16, Film canister c130, 16mm film reels 001_0402)
        Trains with overhead trolley attachment; bus and taxi traffic on city street.
      - Outtakes (Box 16, Film canister c130, 16mm film reels 001_0403)
        Trains and buses, industrial scene, men working in transit maintenance shop, riveting or bolting large metal plates.
      - Outtakes (Box 16, Film canister c130, 16mm film reels 001_0404, 001_0405)
        Press conference by Michael Quill
      - Outtakes (Box 16, Film canister c130, 16mm film reels 001_0401)
        1) Press conference by Michael Quill declaring that the strike is not settled, contrary to reports in the press. 2) Mayor of Philadelphia Richardson Dilworth making negative statements about the strike, against both union and transit company. 3) Matthew Guinan addressing a meeting saying contract offer is unacceptable.
    - Michael Quill Press Release on Railroad Merger, January 15, 1962 (Box 26, 16mm film reels 001_0928, 001_0929)
      See the video reproduction cuid37009 in Subseries I.B.
      TWU film press release; Michael Quill voices union's opposition to the merger of the Pennsylvania and New York Central Railroads.
    - Press Release on Railroad Merger, Strike, January 20, 1962 (Box 19, Film canister c114, 16mm film reels 001_0428)
      Press conference with Michael Quill on the merger of the Pennsylvania and New York Central Railroads and threatened strike against the railroads by Transport Workers Union.
    - Press Release on Airlines Merger, January 24, 1962 (Film canister c109, 16mm film reels 001_0322)
      Matthew Guinan announces union's opposition to proposed merger between Eastern and American Airlines.
    - Emergency Mass Meeting, February 21, 1962 (Film canister c63, 16mm film reels 001_0896)
      See the video reproduction cuid37005 in Subseries I.B.
      Emergency mass meeting called by Transport Workers Union Local 100 to vote on strike resolution against Fifth Avenue Coach Company.
    - Picket Line, Saint Patrick's Day Parade, March, 1962 (Box 26, 16mm film reels 001_0925)
      See the video reproduction cuid37007 in Subseries I.B.
      Transport Workers Union's strikers against the Fifth Avenue Coach Company picket New York Governor Nelson Rockefeller's offices; New York City St. Patrick's Day Parade.
    - Bus Lobbying in Albany, March 7, 1962 (Box 28, 16mm film reels 001_0311)
      Lobbying trip to the New York State Legislature in Albany, by striking New York City bus drivers.
    - Michael Quill on CBS-TV, March 9, 1962 (Box 29, 16mm film reels 001_0894)
      See the video reproduction cuid37006 in Subseries I.B.
      Michael Quill's rebuttal to Roy Cohn and Lawrence Weissman's statements on the TWU strike against the Fifth Avenue Coach Company, televised on the same station the previous night
    - Mass Meeting on Fifth Avenue Coach Company Strike, March 14, 1962 (Box 31, 16mm film reels 001_0887, Box 28, 16mm film reels 001_0926)
      Mass meeting at the Manhattan Center of TWU strikers against Fifth Avenue Coach Company.
    - St. Patrick's Day Parade, Picket Line, March 17, 1962 (Box 28, 16mm film reels 001_0924)
      Transport Workers Union delegation in New York City St. Patrick's Day parade; TWU strike picket line against Fifth Avenue Coach Company.
    - TWU vs Fifth Avenue Coach Company Pension Hearings, November 16, 1962 (Box 19, Film canister c108, 16mm film reels 001_0413, 001_0414, Box 30, 16mm film reels 001_0932)
      See the video reproduction cuid37008 in Subseries I.B.
      Footage from the TWU vs Fifth Avenue Coach Company Pension Hearings, held at the Association of the Bar of the City of New York.
    - Albany Lobbying Trip Compilation, 1962 (Box 33, 16mm film reels 001_0902)
      Picket line and lobbying trip to New York State capitol by strikers during the Transport Workers Union strike against the Fifth Avenue Coach Company; Jimmy Hoffa addressing TWU strikers (voice-over).
    - Albany Lobbying Trip Compilation, 1962 (Box 31, 16mm film reels 001_0888)
      Lobbying trip to New York State Legislature by strikers during Transport Workers Union strike against Fifth Avenue Coach Company; Fifth Avenue Coach Company strike victory meeting; TWU participation in New York City St. Patrick's Day parade.
    - Arbitration hearing before Theodore Kheel on the Fifth Avenue Coach Company, 1962 (Box 31, 16mm film reels 001_0931)
      Poor picture and audio quality.
      Presentations and arguments from both company management and Transport Workers Union officers.
    - End of Bus Strike Announcement, circa 1962 (Box 30, 16mm film reels 001_0923)
      Michael Quill announces end of strike by workers on the New York City Omnibus and Third Avenue bus systems.
    - Fifth Avenue Coach Company Strike, 1962
      - Film (Film canister c181, 16mm film reels 001_0329)
        Demonstration in support of Transport Workers Union's strike against Fifth Avenue Coach Company.
      - Film (Box 26, 16mm film reels 001_0934)
        Transport Workers Union picket line of pensioners of the Fifth Avenue Coach Company.
      - Film (Film canister c115, 16mm film reels 001_0236, Box 33, 16mm film reels 001_0309)
        Transport Workers Union demonstrating against Fifth Avenue Coach Company; street scenes in midtown Manhattan and upper Eastside.
      - Film (Film canister c129, 16mm film reels 001_0252)
        Demonstrations in two locations by TWU strikers against the Fifth Avenue Coach Company.
      - Film (Box 19, Film canister c114, 16mm film reels 001_0429)
        Matthew Guinan speaks at TWU picket of Fifth Avenue Coach Company.
      - Film (Box 19, Film canister c114, 16mm film reels 001_0430)
        TWU pickets Fifth Avenue Coach Company headquarters.
      - Film (Box 30, 16mm film reels 001_0919)
        TWU pickets at the headquarters of the Fifth Avenue Coach Company.
      - Film (Box 30, 16mm film reels 001_0920)
      - Film (Box 30, 16mm film reels 001_0921)
        Matthew Guinan speaks at TWU picket line at Fifth Avenue Coach Company headquarters.
      - Film (Box 30, 16mm film reels 001_0933)
        Picket lines, rallies, meetings during TWU strike against the Fifth Avenue Coach Company.
    - Fifth Avenue Coach Company Strike Victory, circa 1962 (Box 26, 16mm film reels 001_0930)
      Victory demonstration by Transport Workers Union strikers against the Fifth Avenue Coach Company; workers in bus repair shop.
    - Local 100 Strike Resolution Meeting and Hearing, 1962 (Box 17, Film canister c111, 16mm film reels 001_0374)
      Trims of emergency mass meeting called by Transport Workers Union Local 100 to vote on strike resolution against Fifth Avenue Coach Co.; hearing before arbitrator on insolvency of Fifth Avenue Coach Co.
    - Meeting on Fifth Avenue Coach Company Strike, 1962 (Box 31, 16mm film reels 001_0922)
      Annual stockholders' meeting of the Fifth Avenue Coach Company; company pensioners picketing stockholders' meeting.
    - Michael Quill Announcement on Fifth Avenue Coach Company, 1962 (Box 20, 16mm film reels 001_0828)
      Transport Workers Union leader Michael Quill announces the union's intention to become actively involved in the stockholder struggle over the Fifth Avenue Coach Company.
    - Press Release on Settlement, 1962 (Film canister c235, 16mm film reels 001_0031)
      Press conference or filmed press release with Transport Workers Union's Michael Quill on settlement of strike by 3rd Avenue Omnibus and Fifth Avenue Coach Company workers.
    - Press Release on American / Eastern Airlines Merger, circa 1962 (Box 20, 16mm film reels 001_0863)
      Transport Workers Union leaders announce the union's opposition to proposed merger of Eastern and American Airlines.
    - Howard K. Smith Program, January 27, 1963 (Box 25, 16mm film reels 001_0256)
      This is a program in a weekly series hosted by Howard K. Smith. The program examines the problem of current industrial unrest, and the upsurge of strikes. The program includes interviews of Jimmy Hoffa, J. Max Swaggart, Michael Quill, Robert H. Stier, George Taylor, and A.H. Raskin interspersed with stock footage montages.
    - Meeting on Fifth Avenue Coach Company Strike, April 8, 1963 (Film canister c122, 16mm film reels 001_0254)
      Transport Workers Union's John O'Donnell and another man address meeting of Fifth Avenue Coach Company pensioners.
    - Michael Quill Press Release to Nationalize Railroads, June 10, 1963 (Box 16, Film canister c142, 16mm film reels 001_0406, 001_0407, 001_0408, Box 26, 16mm film reels 001_0927)
      Michael Quill announcing the TWU's opposition to the proposed merger of the Pennsylvania and New York Central Railroads. Formal announcement of proposal by TWU to nationalize railroads.
    - Michael Quill Press Conference on NYCTA Strike, October 30, 1963 (Box 32, 16mm film reels 001_0911)
      At a press conference, TWU's Michael Quill discusses breakdown of negotiations with New York Transit Authority and threatened strike.
    - Press Conference with TWU, Amalgamated Streetcar Union, and NYCTA, November 13, 1963 (Film canister c181, 16mm film reels 001_0328)
      Press conference meeting of Transit Labor Mediation Board agreed upon by the Transport Workers Union, Amalgamated Streetcar Union and the New York City Transit Authority. Arbitrated by Theodore Kheel. The press interviews Quill.
    - Mayor Wagner on TWU-NCYTA Negotiations, circa 1963 (Box 32, 16mm film reels 001_0910)
      New York City Mayor Robert Wagner, Jr. reports to press on his discussions with Transport Workers Union officials, New York City Transit Authority officials and mediators on contract negotiations.
    - Negotiations Between TWU and NYCTA, circa 1963 (Film canister c116, 16mm film reels 001_0337)
      This film includes 1) A joint press conference by the Transport Workers Union and the New York City Transit Authority to report on negotiations between the two parties. John O'Donnell, Matthew Guinan, and Michael Quill are present. 2) An open arbitration session between the TWU and NYCTA, including Theodore Kheel. Same content as 001_0338.
    - Philadelphia Strike, 1963 (Film canister c188, 16mm film reels 001_0211)
    - Contract Signing Between TWU and NYCTA, January 28, 1964 (Film canister c110, 16mm film reels 001_0354)
    - Contract Signing Between TWU and NYCTA, January 28, 1964 (Film canister c72, 16mm film reels 001_0308)
      Signing of contract between Transport Workers Union and the New York City Transit Authority; press conference following the signing; report on this contract to a Transport Workers Union body by union officers that includes references to dissidents within the union.
    - Michael Quill on Pennsylvania Railroad Contract, 1964 (Box 28, 16mm film reels 001_0305)
      Transport Workers Union leader Michael Quill announces signing of contract between union and Pennsylvania Railroad.
    - Press Conference Regarding Negotiations Between TWU and NYCTA, circa 1964-1965 (Box 19, Film canister c120, 16mm film reels 001_0418, 001_0419, Box 28, 16mm film reels 001_0304)
      Press conference on contract negotiations between Transport Workers Union and New York City Transit Authority--Michael Quill speaks and unidentified spokesperson for NYCTA speaks.
    - Garment Center Labor Rally to Protest Murder of Emmett Till, October 11, 1965 (Film canister c96, 16mm film reels 001_0333)
      "Garment Center Labor Rally to Protest Murder of Emmett Till and Racist Terror in Mississippi. Tuesday October 11 at 12 noon. Sponsored by District 65 RWDSU-CIO."